so now that we know how to find a block
offset and the block number let's talk
about the cache tags which is how we
determine which block do we actually
have in the cache so our cache can
contain some number of lines in this
case we have a four line cache we could
have something like for example 64 bytes
of data in each line let's say that any
block from memory can be placed in any
of these four lines in that case when we
are given the address by the processor
the least significant bits of the
address will tell us where in the line
we are after we find the line but each
of these lines in the cache could
contain any block number from the memory
so the question is how do we find
whether our access is actually a cache
hit or not and the answer is in addition
to the data of the blocks the cache also
keeps a so called tag that tells it
which block does it have here in this
particular cache the tag will contain
the block number that the cache has in
each of these spots so we need four tags
because there could be four blocks in
this cache so given the address we take
the block number part of the address and
compare it to each of the tags we have
in our cache if one of these says one
that means that the tag matches the
block number and that means that our
data is in the corresponding line in the
cache let's say that this is the
situation we have so we have a tag match
here that means that we have a hit and
that our data is here in the cache now
we can use the block offset to tell us
where in that line our data is and we
take the data and supply to the
processor so in this particular cache we
have the offset part of the address here
and the block number is in this case
called the tag part of the address when
we have a cache miss we will bring the
data here and we will put the block
number in the corresponding tag so that
we can find this block later we will see
later that sometimes the tag part of the
address
is not exactly the same as the block
number but in this cache it is